A Guide to the Thomas Ritchie Correspondence, 1835-1853
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Thomas Ritchie Correspondence, 1835-1853
Library of Virginia
28545
46 pages.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donor information unavailable.
Biographical/Historical Information
Thomas Ritchie was born on 5 November 1778 in Tappahannock, Essex County, Virginia, the son of Archibald and Mary (Roane) Ritchie. He opened a bookstore in Richmond, Virginia in 1803. On 9 May 1804, he co- founded the Richmond Enquirer with W. W. Worsley and became the sole editor and owner a year later. From 1814-1834, 1835-1839, Ritchie served as the state printer and in 1845 was elected congressional printer. At the behest of President James K. Polk, he founded the Washington Union in 1845. Ritchie died in Washington, D.C. on 2 July 1854.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence, 1835-1853 and undated, to Thomas Ritchie, from various individuals concerning politics, newspapers, and slavery.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Jno. O. Lay, Congress Hall, Saratoga, to Thos. Ritchie, Esq., Enq[uire]r office, Richmond, 8 August 1835, 4 p., ALS; Describing his meeting with Van Buren, in which they discussed abolition.
- N. M. Martin, Petersburg, to Thos. Ritchie, Esq., Richmond, 7 October 1843, 2 p., ALS; Discussing the strength of the Republican [Democratic] Party and the convention to nominate its Presidential candidate.
- J. T. Barbour, Catalpa, to T. Ritchie, Esq., 24 July 1845, 4 p., ALS; Discussing Calhoun and his influence in keeping the Republican [Democratic] Party intact, and also, the Senate and party strength within it.
- E. W. Brown, Platte City, Missouri, to [Thomas Ritchie], Washington Union, Washington City, D. C., 2 February 1847, 4 p., ALS; Discussing his "plan for the navigation of the atmosphere by means of the balloon," and desiring to publish his plan so that someone might test it.
- J. T. Barbour, Catalpa, to T. Ritchie, Esq., 29 April 1847, 4 p., ALS
- John Marshall, Mississippian office, to Hon. Thomas Ritchie, Washington, D. C., 9 May 1848, 4 p., ALS; Taking exception to Ritchie's position regarding slavery in California.
- John K. Martin, Colemans Hotel, to Thos. Ritchie, Esq., Washington City, D. C., 30 July 1848, 4 p., ALS; Sending F. R. Blair's statement of his position on Van Buren, Lewis Cass, and William O. Butler.
- John Marshall, New Orleans, to Hon. Thomas Ritchie, 30 September 1848, 4 p., ALS
- John Marshall, Jackson, Mississippi, to Hon. Thos. Ritchie, 29 June 1849, 4 p., ALS; Praising Ritchie's management of the Union [paper] and telling of his own purchase of the Mississippian
- Samuel Treat, St. Louis, to Thomas Ritchie, Esq., Washington, D. C., 30 July 1849, 4 p., ALS; Concerning a man to succeed Capt. Phillips as editor of the St. Louis Union, and also discussing Benton's waning political power.
- W[illia]m Goodwin, Louisa Courthouse, to Mr. Thomas Ritchie, former editor of the R[ichmond] Enquirer,26 May 1853, 4 p., ALS; Requesting information on inquiry procedures concerning the estates of Scottish nobility.
- W[illiam] L[earned] M[arcey], [Secretary of War], to Mr. Tho. Ritchie, ca. 1848-1849, 1 p., ALS, with enclosures; Returning two letters Ritchie had sent - (1) John R. MacMurdo, Treasurer of U. S. Mint, New Orleans, to John Marshall, Esq., concerning the New Orleans Quartermaster's political views, 27 September 1848 (2 p., Ms. copy) and (2) Peter K. Magnus, editor of New Orleans Courier, New Orleans, to J. Marshall, Esq., concerning the New Orleans Quartermaster's political conduct, 27 September 1848 (2 p., Ms. copy)